let's see how to use geometry to find
the exact trig values of multiples of
18° draw an isoceles triangle with base
angles given by 72° vertex angle given
by 36° base length of 1 and a side
length of x to construct this triangle
note that it appears naturally inside a
regular pentagon with side length one
use the angle bis sector of the lower
left 72° angle to create two subt
triangles one of them the one pictured
in yellow has angles of 36° in 72° so
the other angle must also be 72° that
means this yellow triangle is isoceles
so its other leg length is one but then
the other subt triangle the one shown in
purple here has two 36° angles which
means that it's also isoceles and that
means that its other leg length is one
as well and this fact allows us to see
that the base length of the yellow
triangle must be x -1 notice that this
yellow triangle is similar to the
original triangle because they both have
the three same angle measurements but
that means that the ratio x / 1 is equal
to 1 / X - 1 this equation implies that
x^2 - x - 1 must be 0 and the positive
root of this equation is x = 1 + > 5/2
this number is the golden ratio and is
often denoted by the Greek letter Fe
that means the side length of the
original triangle is the golden ratio
and the base length of the yellow
triangle is one less than the golden
ratio here's how we can use use this
diagram to find interesting trig values
first notice that the supplementary
angle to the 72° angle is 108° as shown
here when we BCT the 108° angle like
this cutting the other side in half we
create a right triangle with angles 54°
and 36° and a side length that is half
the golden
ratio we can also bisect the lower left
36° angle like this creating a right
triangle with angles 18° and 72° and a
leg length of the golden ratio - 1 / 2
notice that both these triangles
pictured in blue and purple have a
hypotenuse of length one using the blue
right triangle we see that the S of 54°
is equal to the cosine of 36° and they
are both the golden ratio divided 2
which ends up being the < TK 5 + 1 / 4
from the purple right triangle we see
that the sign of 18° which is equal to
the cosine of 72° is equal to 1 less
than the golden ratio / 2 and this
simplifies to the < TK 5 - 1 4 we've
been able to use this interesting Golden
Triangle to find trig values for various
multiples of 18° can you use the diagram
or perhaps other trig identities to find
the missing trig functions of the
multiples of 18° in the first quadrant
for instance can you find the cosine of
54° or cosine of 18° or the S of 36° and
the S of
72° let me know in the comments and
check out my playlist on trigonometry if
you like this kind of video